Register of the United States. Civil Affairs Training School records
Hoover Institution Archives
United States. Civil Affairs Training School records
1942-1947
XX413
Hoover Institution Archives
59 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box, 3 sound discs (25.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, financial and personnel records, handbooks, syllabi, and instructional materials relating to the politics, governments, economies, and cultures of Japan, other areas in the Pacific, and various countries in Europe; and intelligence assessments of the war in the Pacific. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Stanford University.
United States. Civil Affairs Training School, Stanford University.
Access
Microfilm use only.
Digital copies of all sound recordings are available for immediate access; digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.. To view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (65 reels). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Historical Note
As United States involvement in the Second World War deepened, the American military began to make contingency plans based on the likelihood of an eventual Allied victory and the need for qualified personnel to administer the occupation of liberated countries in Europe and Asia. In 1943, a training program for such personnel was established at Stanford and other universities (including Harvard and the Universities of Chicago and Michigan) under the authority of the Office of the Provost Marshal General of the United States Army. This program, known as the United States Civil Affairs Training School (or CATS) program, drew upon military personnel with experience in civil affairs or with special language abilities. The schools' curricula involved intensive courses in the languages, history, sociology, and culture of the various countries which were considered likely to be occupied by Allied forces. Particular emphasis was placed on the study of the economies of these countries, and exercises were conducted which simulated the kinds of problems likely to be encountered by occupation authorities.
The CATS program drew extensively upon the resources of the universities with which it was associated. At Stanford, university officials and faculty were recruited for the CATS program, and both the staff and the research materials of the Hoover Library played an important role in the program. Because of the need for Japanese language instructors, the CATS program also recruited among the Nisei population in the various relocation camps established after the American entry into the war. These Nisei instructors had to receive special permission from the American military in order to participate in the CATS program.
The CATS program operated at Stanford University from late 1943 until the middle of 1945. Throughout most of this time, its director was Harold Fisher, a Hoover Library official.
Scope and Content Note
The United States Civil Affairs Training School records consist largely of the school's academic and administrative records. There is a large amount of the course material used in classroom instruction (see ACADEMIC FILE), extensive personnel records (see ADMINISTRATIVE FILE), as well as numerous reports and intelligence estimates used for research by students (see RESEARCH MATERIAL). Much of this material gives insights into the concerns of American military planners regarding post-war occupation regimes, as well as indicating the military's perceptions of enemy countries, both as military powers and as socio-cultural formations.
There is material in the collection which discusses the origins of the school, its role within the administrative hierarchy of the Office of the Provost Marshal General, and its relations with other CATS programs (see ADMINISTRATIVE FILE, CORRESPONDENCE, and SUBJECT FILE). The question of the use of Nisei instructors is documented in the personnel records of the school.
Military government.; Sound recordings.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--Occupied territories.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Other Finding Aids note
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- ACADEMIC FILE, 1943-1945 (Boxes 1-13)
  Scope and Contents note
  Assignments, correspondence, dispatches, drills, examinations, exercises, homework, invoices, lectures, memoranda, messages, notes, outlines, printed matter, reports, and syllabi, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Course material, 1943-1945 (Boxes 1-10, Box-folder 11: 1-3)
    Assignments, drills, examinations, exercises, homework, lectures, outlines, and syllabi.
  - Subject file, 1943-1945
    Correspondence, dispatches, invoices, memoranda, messages, notes, reports, and printed matter.
    - Civil Affairs Training School, Actual Demonstration Exercise (CATSADE)
      Material relating to exercises simulating the military occupation of German and Japanese cities.
      - Cologne (Köln) exercise (Box-folder 11: 4-5)
      - Nagasaki exercise (Box-folder 12: 1-4)
    - Motion pictures (Box-folder 12: 5-6, Box-folder 13: 1-3)
- ADMINISTRATIVE FILE, 1943-1947 (Boxes 13-29)
  Announcements, balance sheets, budgets, bulletins, charts, clippings, contract, correspondence, directories, forms, memoranda, personnel records, printed matter, purchase orders, receipts, regulations, reports, requisitions, rules, and schedules, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - General, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
    Notes and miscellany.
  - Announcements and bulletins, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Charts, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Clippings, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Directories, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Financial records, 1943-1946
    - Accounts, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
      Balance sheets and ledger books.
    - Budgets, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 14: 3-4)
      Includes some correspondence.
    - Contract, 1943 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - Requisitions, 1943-1945
      Includes purchase orders and receipts.
      - 1943 (Box-folder 14: 6-7)
      - 1943 (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
      - 1943-1944 (Box-folder 15: 3)
      - 1944 (Box-folder 15: 4)
      - 1944 (Box-folder 16: 1-4)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 16: 5)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 17: 1-5)
  - Forms, undated (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - Memoranda, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 18: 2)
  - Personnel records, 1943-1947
    Correspondence, forms, and memoranda.
    - Faculty
      - General
        - 1943 (Box-folder 18: 3-5)
        - 1944 (Box-folder 18: 6-7)
        - 1945 (Box-folder 19: 1)
      - Language instructors
        - A-F (Box-folder 19: 2)
        - H-I (Box-folder 19: 3)
        - K (Box-folder 19: 4)
        - M (Box-folder 19: 5)
        - N-R (Box-folder 19: 6)
        - S (Box-folder 20: 1)
        - T-Y (Box-folder 20: 2)
      - Visiting lecturers
        - 1944 (Box-folder 20: 3)
        - 1945 (Box-folder 20: 4)
    - Staff (Box-folder 20: 5)
      Includes administrators, secretaries, and technical assistants.
    - Students
      - 1943 (Box-folder 21: 1-5)
      - 1943 (Box-folder 22: 1-3)
      - 1944 (Box-folder 22: 4-5)
      - 1944 (Box-folder 23: 1-4)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 23: 5)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 24: 1-4)
      - 1946-1947 (Box-folder 24: 5)
  - Reports, 1944 (Box-folder 25: 1-2)
  - Rules and regulations, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - Schedules, 1943-1945
    - 1943-1944 (Box-folder 25: 4)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 25: 5-6)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 25: 7)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - Subject file, 1943-1945
    Correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed matter, and reports.
    - Complaints and suggestions (Box-folder 26: 2)
    - Conferences (Box-folder 26: 3)
    - Curriculum development (Box-folder 26: 4-7)
    - Curriculum development (Box-folder 27: 1-3)
    - Draft deferments (Box-folder 27: 4)
    - Equipment (Box-folder 27: 5)
    - Graduation exercises (Box-folder 27: 6)
    - Graduation exercises (Box-folder 28: 1)
    - Housing (Box-folder 28: 2)
    - Language instruction (Box-folder 28: 3)
    - Program origins (Box-folder 28: 4)
    - Public health (Box-folder 28: 5)
    - Room assignments (Box-folder 28: 6)
    - Reviews of materials (Box-folder 28: 7)
    - Sacramento project (Box-folder 28: 8)
    - Salaries (Box-folder 28: 9)
    - Security clearances (Box-folder 28: 10)
    - Textbooks (Box-folder 29: 1)
    - Travel (Box-folder 29: 2)
    - United States Army, Western Defense Command (Box-folder 29: 3)
    - United States Army Service Forces, Army Specialized Training Division, 9-L (Box-folder 29: 4)
    - United States War Relocation Authority
      - Manzanar, California (Box-folder 29: 5)
      - Topaz, Utah (Box-folder 29: 6)
  - Telephone bills (Box-folder 29: 7)
    Includes correspondence.
  - Yearbook (three printed copies) (Box-folder 29: 8)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1942-1945 (Boxes 29-31)
  Letters and memoranda addressed to individuals, organized by name of school official sending or receiving correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by name of school official.
  - Allen, Frank, 1944 (Box-folder 29: 9)
  - Anderson, Ronald, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 29: 10)
  - Eden, John, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 29: 11)
  - Fisher, Harold
    - 1943
      - May-August (Box-folder 30: 1)
      - September (Box-folder 30: 2)
      - October-November (Box-folder 30: 3)
      - December (Box-folder 30: 4)
    - 1944
      - January-February (Box-folder 30: 5)
      - March-June (Box-folder 30: 6)
      - July-December (Box-folder 30: 7)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 31: 1)
  - Hanna, Paul, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 31: 2)
  - Lavrov, Sergey, 1944 (Box-folder 31: 3)
  - Lutz, Ralph, 1943 (Box-folder 31: 4)
  - Patten, Nathan van, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 31: 5)
  - Sokol, Anthony, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 31: 6)
  - Thomas, Lawrence
    - 1943 (Box-folder 31: 7)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 31: 8)
    - 1945
      - January-June (Box-folder 31: 9)
      - July-August (Box-folder 31: 10)
- LIBRARY FILE, 1943-1945 (Boxes 32-34)
  Acquisition records, bibliographies, circulation records, correspondence, filing index, holdings records, loan records, memoranda, printed matter, and reports, arranged alphabetically by physical form. See also: CARD FILE.
  - General, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 32: 1-2)
    Correspondence and reports.
  - Acquisition records, 1943-1945
    Consists largely of lists of materials received.
    - 1943-1944 (Box-folder 32: 3)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 32: 4-5)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 32: 6)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 33: 1-3)
  - Bibliographies, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 33: 4)
  - Circulation records, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 33: 5)
  - Filing index, 1944 (Box-folder 33: 6)
  - Holdings records, 1943 (Box-folder 33: 7)
  - Loan records (Box-folder 34: 1)
  - Memoranda (Box-folder 34: 2)
  - Subject file, 1943-1945
    Correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter.
    - Book and map orders (Box-folder 34: 3-5)
    - Disposition of material (Box-folder 34: 6)
- OFFICE OF THE PROVOST MARSHAL GENERAL FILE, 1943-1945 (Boxes 34-37)
  The U.S. Civil Affairs Training School program was under the adminstrative supervision of the Office of the Provost Marshal General of the U.S. Army, and the Stanford school reported directly to this office. Correspondence, memoranda, organizational charts, and reports, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Correspondence, 1943-1945
    - General, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 34: 7)
    - Fielding, William, 1944 (Box-folder 34: 8)
    - Gorman, Robert, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 34: 9)
    - Gullion, Allen, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 34: 10)
    - Heffner, Hubert, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 35: 1)
    - Hyneman, Charles, 1943 (Box-folder 35: 2)
    - Lerch, Archer, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 35: 3)
    - Miller, Jesse, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 35: 4)
    - Moulton, William, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 35: 5)
    - Robison, H. E., 1943-1945 (Box-folder 35: 6)
    - Shoemaker, James, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 35: 7)
    - Storer, Morris, 1944 (Box-folder 35: 8)
    - Van Wagenen, Richard, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 35: 9)
  - Memoranda, 1943-1945
    - 1943 (Box-folder 35: 10)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 36: 1)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 36: 2)
  - Organizational charts, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 36: 3)
  - Reports, 1944-1945
    - 1944 (Box-folder 36: 4)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 36: 5-6)
  - Subject file, 1943-1945
    Correspondence and memoranda.
    - Book orders (Box-folder 36: 7)
    - Lecturers (Box-folder 37: 1)
    - Translations (Box-folder 37: 2)
- PUBLICATIONS FILE, 1944-1945 (Boxes 37-42)
  Material relating to publications produced by the U.S. Civil Affairs Training School, Stanford University. Correspondence, drafts, outlines, printed matter, and questionnaires, arranged chronologically and by degree of completion.
  - Special Reports on Germany Prepared by Officer Students of the Civil Affairs Training School at Stanford Unversity, printed copies, undated (Box-folder 37: 3-4)
  - Civil Affairs Handbook on Japan (1944), 1944-1945
    Sections 1, 6, and 16 of this handbook were produced at Stanford.
    - Correspondence, 1944-1945
      - A-F (Box-folder 37: 5)
      - G-M (Box-folder 37: 6)
      - O-Z (Box-folder 37: 7)
    - Questionnaires, 1944 (Box-folder 38: 1-5)
      Includes responses.
    - Outlines, 1944 (Box-folder 39: 1)
    - Preliminary drafts, 1944 (Box-folder 39: 2-5)
    - Preliminary drafts, 1944 (Box-folder 40: 1)
    - Final draft, 1944 (Box-folder 40: 2-5)
    - Printed copy (provisional edition), 1944
      - Section 1, Geographical and social background (Box-folder 40: 6)
      - Section 1, Geographical and social background (Box-folder 41: 1-2)
      - Section 6, Natural resources (Box-folder 41: 3-5)
      - Section 16, Public welfare (Box-folder 41: 6)
      - Section 16, Public welfare (Box-folder 42: 1-2)
- RESEARCH MATERIAL, 1943-1945 (Boxes 42-56)
  Printed material, much of it orginally classified or otherwise restricted, used by students and faculty of the U.S. Civil Affairs Training School at Stanford University. Intelligence digests and estimates, reports, and translations, arranged by physical form. See also: DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS.
  - Intelligence digests and estimates, 1943-1945
    - General (Box-folder 42: 3)
    - Counterintelligence (Box-folder 42: 4)
    - Germany (Box-folder 42: 5)
    - Italy (Box-folder 42: 6)
    - Japan and the Pacific Theater
      - General (Box-folder 42: 7-8)
      - General (Box-folder 43: 1-2)
      - Far East Intelligence Notes (Box-folder 43: 3-5)
        Material prepared by the Office of Strategic Services.
  - Reports, 1943-1946
    Includes material prepared by various intelligence agencies.
    - General
      - General (Box-folder 43: 6)
      - General (Box-folder 44: 1-3)
      - Military Government Field Reports (Box-folder 44: 4-5)
        Issued by the Office of the Chief of Naval Operations, U.S. Navy Department.
    - Albania (Box-folder 45: 1)
    - China (Box-folder 45: 2)
    - France (Box-folder 45: 3)
    - Germany (Box-folder 45: 4-6)
    - Germany (Box-folder 46: 1)
    - Indochina (Box-folder 46: 2)
    - Italy (Box-folder 46: 3)
    - Japan
      - General (Box-folder 46: 4)
      - Airfields (Box-folder 46: 5)
      - Economic conditions
        - General (Box-folder 47: 1-5)
        - General (Box-folder 48: 1-5)
        - General (Box-folder 49: 1-2)
        - Fishing industry (Box-folder 49: 3)
        - Iron and steel industries (Box-folder 49: 4-5)
        - Power industry (Box 50)
          Material produced by the Office of Strategic Services (incomplete).
        - Power industry (Box-folder 51: 1-2)
      - Politics and government (Box-folder 51: 3-4)
      - Ports (Box-folder 52: 1-4)
      - Ports (Box-folder 53: 1-4)
      - Russo-Japanese War (1904-1905) (Box-folder 54: 1)
      - Transportation
        - General (Box-folder 54: 2)
        - Railroads (Box-folder 54: 3-4)
    - Netherlands (Box-folder 54: 5)
    - Philippines (Box-folder 54: 6)
    - Russia (see: Japan/Russo-Japanese War (1904-1905))
  - Translations, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 55: 1-4, Box-folder 56: 1-4)
    Articles translated into English from the Japanese press and government publications.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1943-1945 (Boxes 57-59)
  Correspondence, instructional material, notes, printed matter, reports, and serial issue, arranged alphabetically subject.
  - Captured German documents (Box-folder 57: 1-2)
    Target lists of documents captured or sought by the American military (not the documents themselves).
  - Japanese Americans (Box-folder 57: 3)
  - United States Army, School of Military Government, Charlottesville, Virginia (Box-folder 57: 4)
  - United States Civil Affairs Holding and Staging Area, Presidio of Monterey (Box-folder 57: 5-7)
  - United States Civil Affairs Holding and Staging Area, Presidio of Monterey (Box-folder 58: 1)
  - United States Civil Affairs Training School
    - Harvard University (Box-folder 58: 2)
    - Northwestern University (Box-folder 58: 3)
    - University of Chicago (Box-folder 58: 4-5)
    - University of Michigan (Box-folder 59: 1-3)
    - Yale University (Box-folder 59: 4)
- CARD FILE, 1943-1945 (Box 60)
  Card catalog listing holdings in the Hoover Library used by the U.S. Civil Affairs Training School, Stanford University.
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, 1945, undated (Record cabinet, Box 59)
  - Photograph of class trip to Yosemite National Park, 1945 (Box-folder 59: 5)
  - Colonel Diller commencement speech at the School of Military Government, 1945? (Record cabinet)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: xx413_a_0005704
    Diller speaks to military students about to enter World War II as planners for the military government in the Far East. He begins by explaining to the audience what they can expect at the CASA (Civil Affairs Training Area) at the Presidio of Monterey in California. He says comparing Charlottesville, the location of the School of Military Government, and CASA is analogous to comparing Athens and Sparta. He also speaks about the war. Three sound discs.
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS, 1944-1945 (Box 59, Reading room workstation)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfield, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2010 release of records, 1944-1945, undated (Reading room workstation)
    Includes preliminary drafts of the Civil Affairs Handbook on Italy, Sections 1, 3, 8, 10, 13-16 (undated); memoranda (undated); and reports produced by the Office of Strategic Services, particularly the Research and Analysis Branch (1944-1945). Available as PDF files.
  - 2016 February release of records, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 59: 6)
    Memoranda from the War Department, Adjutant General's Office, to Command Generals enclosing Counter Intelligence Corps Information Bulletins. Includes Bulletin No. 9 (sent 8 December 1944), Bulletin No. 10 (sent 12 February 1945), and Bulletin No. 11 (24 June 1945).